{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A 2010 redesign of this item removed the initials “VDB” from its front for the second time. During World War Two, these items were subject to a discoloring redox reaction when the chemistry-unaware Henry Morgenthau [[mohr-GEHN-thow]] authorized the addition of zinc to them. As a result, one of the most valuable examples of these items is the 1944 “steel wheat” variety. Since 2010 these items display a shield reading “e pluribus unum.” For ten points, name these coins which show Abraham Lincoln on the front.",
      "answer": "U.S. penny or pennies"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this campaign, a combined 25 American and British planes crashed, with 101 fatalities overall. Gail Halvorsen dropped candy to awaiting children during this prolonged campaign, becoming known as the \"Chocolate Flier.\" After the Deutsche [[DOY-chuh]] Mark was introduced, Soviet troops cut off road and rail access to supply an occupied city, immediately causing this event. For ten points, name this aerial campaign led by the United States to provide aid and supplies to the German capital.",
      "answer": [
        "Berlin Airlift",
        "Operation Vittles"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Marco Polo, a ruler of this city was locked in his treasure room without food or water for neglecting to spend his gold on the city’s defense. That ruler of this city, Al- Musta’sim [[al-moo-stah-SEEM]], legendarily died after being rolled in a carpet and trampled to death by an invader’s horses. Harun al-Rashid built a library in this city, which was destroyed in a 1258 siege by Hulagu [[hoo-LAH-goo]] Khan. For ten points, name this city which contained a “House of Wisdom” before becoming the capital of modern-day Iraq.",
      "answer": "Baghdad"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to his money struggles, this philosopher was offered fifty years pay in advance by Catherine the Great to serve as her personal librarian. Pope Clement XIII [[the Thirteenth]] banned a compendium written by this man, citing its skepticism of Jesus' miracles. Alongside Jean d'Alembert [[dahl-ehm-BARE]], this man compiled a \"systematic dictionary of the sciences, arts, and crafts.\" The chief editor of the Encyclopédie [[ohn-see-cloh-PEH-dee]] was, for ten points, which French philosopher?",
      "answer": "Denis Diderot ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early lyric by this group parodies the nativist views of Enoch Powell and demands that immigrants return to their “commonwealth homes.” This group's members took an ill- fated trip to Rishikesh [[ree-shee-KESH]] for a guided meditation course with Maharishi Mahesh Yogi. A member of this group left that course early to film the documentary Raga about his sitar teacher, Ravi Shankar. For ten points, name this influential band of the British Invasion whose songs “Get Back” and “Norwegian Wood” were credited to John Lennon and Paul McCartney.",
      "answer": "The Beatles"
    },
    {
      "question": "For use on this ship, Louis Casella manufactured a resilient version of a Six's thermometer. Charles W. Thomson supervised the team of naturalists aboard this vessel, whose equipment included over 181 miles of hemp rope. This vessel, commanded by George Nares and Frank Thomson, became the first to measure the depth of an area at the south end of the Mariana Trench. A four-year 1870s oceanographic expedition was undertaken by, for ten points, what Royal Navy vessel, after which the deepest point in the Marianas Trench was named?",
      "answer": [
        "HMS Challenger",
        "Challenger Deep"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "English physician Thomas Sydenham wrote a 17th century manual advocating for a product containing this good, laudanum. Soldiers from the Kuomintang organized what became the \"Golden Triangle\" for production of this good while operating in Laos, Thailand and Myanmar. European traders sold this good to circumvent the Canton system, which exclusively required silver be spent to acquire goods like tea and porcelain. The Qing [[CHING]] and British empires fought two wars named for, for ten points, what illicit drug later used to produce heroin?",
      "answer": [
        "Opium poppy",
        "Opium Wars",
        "Opium Triangle",
        "or Opium Crescent"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Under these laws, a high concrete wall was used to divide off the Eight Mile-Wyoming Area. Ferris State University contains a memorabilia museum that houses artifacts related to these laws, which created a \"ghetto domestic sector.\" These laws were almost circumvented in the 1875 Civil Rights Act, which the Supreme Court ruled unconstitutional. Leading to \"colored\" restrooms being a norm, for ten points, what were these racial segregation laws in the Southern United States?",
      "answer": "Jim Crow Laws"
    },
    {
      "question": "The deflection of this element’s particles led to J. J. Thomson’s discovery of atomic isotopes. It’s not krypton, but British chemist Sir William Ramsay and Morris W. Travers isolated this element in 1898 and named it for the Greek word for “New.” As a byproduct of air liquefaction, this element was shown by Georges Claude to be able to produce light in sealed tubes. For ten points, name this element historically used for signs in Las Vegas.",
      "answer": [
        "Neon",
        "Ne before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At the behest of Eugene Reybold, a project focused on this river employed a number of Camp Clinton-housed prisoners from the German Afrika Korps. A series of levees were built along this river in the aftermath of an event that bolstered Huey Long’s gubernatorial campaign and resulted in Herbert Hoover leading a series of relief operations. That piece of legislation also mandated the creation of the Birds Point-New Madrid Floodway along this river. For ten points, name this major American river that experienced a “great” 1927 flood.",
      "answer": "Mississippi River"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Working with General David Canaberro, this general established the Juliana Republic in southern Brazil. This man was infuriated by an agreement made at Plombières [[plohm- BEE-air]], which promised to cede his home city of Nice to France. This leader of the \"Hunters of the Alps\" aligned with the Colorados during the Uruguayan Civil War, after which he returned to his home country to lead the Expedition of the Thousand to Sicily. For ten points, name this Italian general, considered a father of the First Italian Republic.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi or Giuseppe Maria Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Italian statesman, who reluctantly negotiated the cessation of Savoy to France in the Treaty of Plombières, became the first prime minister of Italy?",
        "answer": [
          "Camillo Benso, Count of Cavour",
          "either underlined answer",
          "Camillo Paolo Filippo Giulio Benso, Count of Cavour, Isolabella and Leri"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The fanfare Buckaroo Holiday begins a ballet by this composer, whose choreographer, Agnes de Mille, later worked on the thematically similar Oklahoma!. Martha Graham earned a Pulitzer Prize for her work with this composer for a piece which celebrates the American pioneer and includes a reworking of the Shaker hymn \"Simple Gifts.\" Rodeo, Fanfare for the Common Man, and Appalachian Spring were written by, for ten points, which American composer?",
        "answer": "Aaron Copland ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Copland composed a work named for which outlaw who was gunned down by Pat Garrett in 1881?",
        "answer": [
          "Billy the Kid",
          "William Bonney"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "For years, scholars suspected that several frescoes in the Hall of the Five Hundred at the Palazzo Vecchio were painted over this man's historical work, The Battle of Anghiari. Under the patronage of Ludovico Sforza, this man developed a design for a \"turtle-shell\" fighting vehicle as well as a self-propelled cart and an automaton, though most of his work went unpublished due to being written in a secretive mirror script. For ten points, name this painter and inventor who is considered the consummate \"Renaissance Man.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Leonardo da Vinci",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leonardo's Codex Atlanticus contains a design for a \"rapid-fire\" example of this weapon, which was notably wielded by an internationally-recruited medieval mercenary force from Genoa.",
        "answer": [
          "Crossbow",
          "Genoese Crossbowmen"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This acquisition was retroactively confirmed by the decision American Insurance Co. v. Canter. Secretary of the Treasury Albert Gallatin informed the sitting president that this acquisition was protected by the treaty-making provision in the Constitution. The costliness of the Haitian revolution led to this sale of territory by Napoleon to the United States. The Jefferson administration facilitated, for ten points, what \"Purchase\" which doubled the size of the United States?",
        "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The territory of the Louisiana Purchase was explored by which duo of officers who led the Corps of Discovery?",
        "answer": [
          "Lewis and Clark or Merriweather Lewis and William Clark",
          "in either order"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An invention produced by Andreas Flocken is often considered the first \"true\" one of these objects, which were also produced by Walter Bersey in London. The development of MOSFET helped spark the modern commercial interest in these objects, whose first mass- produced example was the Roadster. Initially eclipsed by the emergence of internal- combustion engine vehicles, for ten points, what are these vehicles run entirely without gasoline, including the popular Tesla Model 3?",
        "answer": "Electric Car"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first six land-speed records were broken by electric vehicles, primarily in France, though for several decades the record was broken by gasoline-powered cars at what recently- deteriorated site in Utah?",
        "answer": [
          "Bonneville Salt Flats",
          "Bonneville Speedway"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Successful commanders from this kingdom were often equated to the god Montu, a war deity who takes the shape of a bull. This polity employed the Medjay, a distinct Cushitic speaking people who served as a paramilitary police force. This kingdom created the sickle shaped sword meant for close-combat known as the Khopesh, and its military mass-adopted the chariot after being invaded by the Hyksos [[HIK-sohs]]. For ten points, name this ancient African kingdom which fought at the Battles of Megiddo and the Nile Delta.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Egypt",
          "Aegypttos",
          "Kemet"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The invading Hyksos were likely from what Levantine region? The Biblical Promised Land corresponds to this region, which included Philistia and Phoenicia.",
        "answer": [
          "Canaan",
          "Kenaʿn",
          "Canaanites"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tyrant of this city named Dionysius the Elder arrested the philosopher Plato and sold him into slavery following a disagreement. A former general of Pyrrhus of Epirus, Hiero II, served as a tyrant of this city, becoming a client of Rome during the First Punic War. Archimedes allegedly used a parabolic reflector to defend this city from a Roman attack, inventing the first \"heat ray.\" For ten points, name this ancient Greek colony in the southeast of Sicily.",
        "answer": [
          "Syracuse",
          "Syracusa",
          "or Sarausa",
          "or Syracusae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first settlers to Syracuse were from which Greek city-state which shares its name with an isthmus that connects Attica and the Peloponnese?",
        "answer": "Corinth or Korinthos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A subset of the \"Great Railroad Strike of 1877\" in this city included strikers trapping police officers on the Halsted Street bridge in the Battle of the Viaduct. During the \"Red Summer,\" this city suffered a race riot on its South Side after African-American teen Eugene Williams was killed for swimming near an \"All-White\" beach. This city's Hyde Park neighborhood hosted the Columbian Exposition of 1893. Hull House was founded in, for ten points, which Midwestern city that suffered a \"Great Fire\" in the 1870s?",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Contributing to the violence of the Chicago Race Riot, the Hamburg Athletic Club, which included future mayor Richard J. Daley, was composed primarily of what white immigrant ethnic group that fiercely guarded neighborhoods like Bridgeport and Back of the Yards.",
        "answer": "Irish-Americans"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Oregon",
      "prompt": "Concerning the state of Oregon, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Largest city in Oregon whose founder named it for his home city in Maine.",
          "answer": "Portland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city possibly named for a site of witch trials in Massachusetts.",
          "answer": "Salem"
        },
        {
          "question": "River on which the Grand Coulee Dam was built during the Great Depression.",
          "answer": "Columbia River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain whose disastrous 1980 eruption covered parts of Washington and Oregon in ash.",
          "answer": "Mount Saint Helens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who was the first European to discover Hawaii and who later mapped parts of the Oregon coast.",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American millionaire whose Pacific Fur Company founded a namesake settlement in Oregon.",
          "answer": [
            "John Jacob Astor",
            "Astoria"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Indigenous people who practiced headbinding, now known for being the namesake of a U.S. Army transport helicopter.",
          "answer": "Chinook"
        },
        {
          "question": "1840s \"incident\" where a black man killed a Casco native over a horse, leading to passage of Oregon's anti-Black settlement laws.",
          "answer": "Cockstock Incident"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Iron Curtain",
      "prompt": "Concerning the ideological division of Europe during the Cold War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Polish capital which names a \"Pact\" of Communist nations led by the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": [
            "Warsaw",
            "Warsaw Pact"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British prime minister who coined the term \"Iron Curtain\" in a 1946 speech.",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill or Winston Leonard Spencer Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "1949 Collective Security organization including most Western European nations and the United States.",
          "answer": [
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization",
            "NATO"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference in Crimea where the Allies agreed on how to split Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Yalta Conference",
            "Argonaut"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Movement\" advocated by the likes of Kwame Nkrumah and Josip Tito as an alternative to the Eastern and Western blocs.",
          "answer": [
            "Non-Aligned Movement",
            "NAM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation whose dictator Enver Hoxha [[HOH-shah]] re-aligned his state from the USSR to Communist China in the 1960s.",
          "answer": "People's Socialist Republic of Albania or Republika Popullore Socialiste e Shqipërisë"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German prime minister whose forced resignation in 1989 paved the way for a unified Germany.",
          "answer": "Erich Honecker or Erich Ernst Paul Honecker"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Doctrine\" named for an American singer which Mikhail Gorbachev adopted, allowing neighbors to deal with their own internal affairs.",
          "answer": "Sinatra Doctrine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apartheid",
      "prompt": "In the apartheid era, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Daniel Malan formalized apartheid in 1948?",
          "answer": "Republic of South Africa or RSA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime prisoner who negotiated an end to apartheid with F.W. de Klerk before becoming president?",
          "answer": "Nelson Mandela or Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decade in which apartheid was dismantled and multiracial elections first took place?",
          "answer": "1990s"
        },
        {
          "question": "1960 incident in which police killed 69 anti-passbook protestors?",
          "answer": "Sharpeville Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular English sport played on the controversial \"Springbok tour\" in 1981?",
          "answer": "Rugby union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Common name for the Black \"homelands\" granted sham independence starting in 1972?",
          "answer": "Bantustans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resort that named a 1985 pro-boycott song composed by Steven Van Zandt?",
          "answer": "Sun City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Black Consciousness Movement who died in police custody in 1977?",
          "answer": "Steve Biko or Bantu Stephen Biko"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1937, this organization became the namesake of an orchestra conducted by Arturo Toscanini that transformed into the Symphony of the Air in 1954. This organization hired Peter Adler to conduct a namesake Opera Theatre that premiered Amahl and (20 pts)",
        "the Night Visitors in 1951. Doc Severinsen, Max Weinberg, and Kevin Eubanks have led in-house bands on this company's late-night (10 pts)",
        "shows. For ten points, name this radio and TV network which trademarked the three-chime sequence that plays over its peacock logo."
      ],
      "answer": "NBC or National Broadcasting Company"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A tableau by this artist depicts the historical Battle of Taillebourg [[TIE-bur]] during the Saintonge [[sahn-TAHNG]] War. While an attaché to a diplomatic envoy to the Kingdom of (20 pts)",
        "Morocco, this artist painted the Orientalist work Women of Algiers. The toppling of Charles X [[the Tenth]] is represented by this artist in a painting depicting a bare-breasted women carrying the tricolour [[tree-koh-LOHR]] flag of France. Liberty (10 pts)",
        "Leading the People was painted by, for ten points, which French Romantic artist?"
      ],
      "answer": "Eugène Delacroix or Ferdinand Victor Eugène Delacroix"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 2020 senate election in this U.S. state, a conspiracy theorist who claims to have invented e-mail, Shiva Ayyadurai, was defeated in the Republican primary. The kidnapping of Colin Bower's children and the police killing of DJ (20 pts)",
        "Henry became issues in this state's Democratic primary, which determined who would face Republican nominee Kevin O'Connor. A congressman from a political dynasty in this state lost the primary to incumbent Ed (10 pts)",
        "Markey. For ten points, name this state from which Markey continues to serve as senator alongside Elizabeth Warren."
      ],
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This non-Chinese figure trained at the Whampoa Military Academy and offered David Ben-Gurion and the Jewish people a homeland in his nation. This politician used the pseudonym \"Nguyen [[WHEN]] the (20 pts)",
        "Patriot\" while writing articles prior to the Versailles Peace Talks. This man led the 1945 August General Uprising which successfully deposed the colonial French following the nine-year First (10 pts)",
        "Indochina War. The city of Saigon was renamed in honor of, for ten points, which first president of communist Vietnam?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ho Chi Minh or Nguyễn Sinh Cung"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this man’s final run for office, he defeated mayor Emory Folmar after narrowly winning the Democratic primary against Lieutenant Governor George McMillan. During one of his four runs for president, this man survived an assassination attempt which left him paralyzed (20 pts)",
        "below the waist. This man briefly served as First Gentleman after his wife, Lurleen, became (10 pts)",
        "Alabama’s first female governor. For ten points, name this long-time Alabama politician who once declared “segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Wallace",
        "George Corley Wallace Jr."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Soe Naing was the first of over a hundred journalists from this nation to be imprisoned in 2021, with many being placed in the Insein Prison first run by the State Law and Order (20 pts)",
        "Restoration Council. 2020 election results in this nation were annulled following a coup by the Tatmadaw [[taht-MAH-\"tau\"]] armed forces. That coup removed Aung (10 pts)",
        "San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] from power in, for ten points, which southeast Asian nation, once known as Burma?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Myanmar",
        "Republic of the Union of Myanmar",
        "or Pyidaunzu Thanmăda Myăma Nainngandaw",
        "Burma before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man compared the extinction of civilization to that of a species in his 1910 Romanes lecture Biological Analogies in History. A late 1880s winter killed much of this man's cattle, forcing him to abandon his ranching venture at Elkhorn. With his son, (20 pts)",
        "Kermit, this man headed a namesake expedition with the Smithsonian, collecting over 11,000 animal specimens and authoring African Game Trails. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this U.S. president, whose saving of a cub led to the creation of his namesake stuffed bear."
      ],
      "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt Jr. or Teddy Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Medieval historian Roger of Wendover claimed that this man offered to convert to Islam if Muhammad al-Nasir lent him military support. This man's refusal to appoint sub-prior Reginald to the post of Archbishop of (20 pts)",
        "Canterbury led to his temporary excommunication by Innocent III. This king was temporarily deposed by the French King, Louis the Lion, after he captured half of England during the First (10 pts)",
        "Barons' War. For ten points, name this brother of Richard the Lionheart and signer of the Magna Carta."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "King John",
        "John Lackland"
      ]
    }
  ]
}